Guide to the Montana Cycling Collection 1976-2014
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Montana Cycling collection
1976-2014
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Pam 13
3.6 linear foot
This is a compiled collection of magazines, newsletters, directories, and other resources related to bike riding, touring and cycling safety in Montana. The bulk of the collection consists of publications produced by BikeCentennial (later known as Adventure Cycling) and the Missoula Bicycle Club (known for a time as Missoulians on Bicycles). Most of the materials were published in Missoula.
This 'artificial' collection contains magazines, newsletters, directories, flyers, posters, and postcards published primarily in Missoula, Montana, related to cyling, bicycle safety, tours, and special events. The bulk of the collection consists of publications from BikeCentennial (known since 1993 as the Adventure Cycling Association) and the Missoula Bicycle Club (known from 1997-2019 as Missoulians on Bicycles, or MOBI). Miscellaneous newsletters related to bicycling created by the City of Missoula and the Montana Transportation Project are also included.
BikeCentennial began as the planning organization of a cross-country bicycle tour commemorating the United States bicentennial in 1976 and later expanded to charting additional long-distance routes for cyclists. In 1993, the group rebranded as Adventure Cycling Association and continues to operate today.
The Missoula Bicycle Club was also established in 1976 as a non-profit promoting safe cycling in Montana. From 1997-2019, the organization was known as Missoulians on Bicycles (MOBI), but it has since reverted its name to the Missoula Bicycle Club.
Prominent publications in this collection include: Bikereport, Adventure Cyclist, Cyclosource, The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, and the Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians on Bicycles Newsletter.
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Missoula Bicycle Club/Missoulians on Bicycles Publications and Promotional Materials, 1977-2014, 1.4 linear feet
Series II: BikeCentennial/Adventure Cycling Association Publications and Promotional Materials, 1976-2009, 2.2 linear feet
Series III: Miscellaneous Newsletters and Flyers, 1980-2002, 1 folder
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Some of these materials were held by Greg Siple/Missoula Bicycle Club prior to their transfer to The University of Montana between 1988 and 1990. Mansfield Library maintained subscriptions to most of the BikeCentennial/Adventure Cycling Association publications and collected them as they were published. The miscellaneous newsletters located in the Series III were originally part of the Montana Pamphlet Collection and were incorporated into this collection in 2014.
Gift of Greg Siple and the Missoula Bicycle Club, circa 1988-1990.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Missoulians on Bicycles; Cycling
- Missoula Bicycle Club/Missoulians on Bicycles Publications and Promotional Materials, 1977-2014; Series I; 1.4 linear feet
  Series I contains the Missoula Bicycle Club/Missoulians on Bicycles Newsletter as well as promotional material related to the Tour of the Swan River Valley (TOSRV), an annual 200+ mile bike tour through western Montana, which was hosted by the club from 1971-2017.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1985 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1986 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1987 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1988 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1989 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1990 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1991 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1992 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1993 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1994 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1995 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1996 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1997 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1998 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 1999 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2000 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2001 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2002 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2003 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2004 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2005 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2006 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2007 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2008 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2009 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2010 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2011 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2012 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Missoula Bike Club / Missoulians On Bicycles Newsletter, 2014 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Tour of the Swan River Valley (TOSRV) Posters and Flyers, 1977-2001; The Tour of the Swan River Valley was an annual 200+ mile bike tour through western Montana, which was hosted by the Missoula Bike Club from 1971-2017. (Box-folder OS 8/1)
  - Tour of the Swan River Valley (TOSRV) postcards, circa 1980s-1990s; Postcards featuring photographs of cyclists participating in the TOSRV. (Box-folder 1/30)
- BikeCentennial/Adventure Cycling Association Publications and Promotional Materials, 1976-2009; Series II; 2.2 linear feet
  Series II contains publications and promotional material from BikeCentennial, which re-branded as the Adventure Cycling Association in 1993. Primary titles include BikeReport, Adventure Cyclist, Cyclosource, and The Cyclists' Yellow Pages.
  - BikeReport, 1976 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - BikeReport, 1977 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - BikeReport, 1978 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - BikeReport, 1979 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - BikeReport, 1980 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - BikeReport, 1981 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - BikeReport, 1982 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - BikeReport, 1983 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - BikeReport, 1983-1984 (Box-folder OS 8/2)
  - BikeReport, 1984 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - BikeReport, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - BikeReport, 1985 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - BikeReport, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - BikeReport, 1986 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - BikeReport, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - BikeReport, 1987 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - BikeReport, 1988 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - BikeReport, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - BikeReport, 1989 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - BikeReport, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - BikeReport, 1990 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - BikeReport, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - BikeReport, 1991 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - BikeReport, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - BikeReport, 1992 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - BikeReport, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - BikeReport, 1993 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - BikeReport, 1994 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1994 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1995 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1996 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1997 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1998 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 1999 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2000 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2001 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2002 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2003 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2004 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2005 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2006 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2007 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Adventure Cyclist, 2008 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Cyclosource, 1992 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Cyclosource, 1993 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Cyclosource, 1997 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Cyclosource, 2002 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Cyclosource, 2003 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Cyclosource, 2004 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Cyclosource, 2005 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Cyclosource, 2006 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1998 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 1999 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2000 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2001 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2002 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2003 (Box-folder 6/16)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2004 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2005 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2006 (Box-folder 6/19)
  - The Cyclists' Yellow Pages, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 6/20)
  - BikeCentennial Tours, 1988-1993; Promotional material for guided tours (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Adventure Cycling Association Tours, 1994-2006; Promotional material for guided tours (Box-folder 7/2)
- Miscellaneous Newsletters and Flyers, 1980-2002; Series III; 1 folder
  Series III contains miscellaneous newsletters and flyers from the City of Missoula's Bicycle Program/Bicycle Pedestrian Office, Police Department, and the Montana Transportation Project, which was a non-profit based out of Helena, Montana.
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters and Flyers, 1980-2002; The City Cyclist. Vol. 1, No. 2. Missoula: Missoula City Bicycle Program, 1980.; Missoula Bike News. Missoula: Missoula City Bicycle Program, 1981-1982 (three issues); Missoula Cyclist. Fall 1990. A Newsletter for Bicyclists and Pedestrians. Missoula: Missoula Bicycle Program, 1990.; The Montana Transportation Project. Helena: Alternative Energy Resources Organization (AERO), 1993.; Amended Bicycle Ordinances. Missoula: Missoula City Police Department, n.d. (two copies); Bike Walk Bus Week 2002. Missoula: City of Missoula Bicycle Pedestrian Office, 2002. (Box-folder 7/3)